( tense sombre music )
- [ Woman ] To my daughter , Linda Mary Stevens ,
I leave my entire inheritance .
All goods , chattles and worldly possessions
that comprise the estate of Montclare .
- [ Radio Reporter ] Thunderstorms bringing in
a cooler change later on today .
There 'll be some rain again tonight
and tomorrow we can expect yet another fine
and warm day .
While we 're talking in the studio today ,
( drowned out by gravel and car revving )
( zooming )
residents in the area or even the tourists
that might be listening would like to run over
a few of these procedures for us .
- [ Man ] Certainly would , Ryan .
And needless to say there 's a fire ban on lighting fires
in the open right now .
We should clear all combustible materials
from around your home or your caravan even .
And all rubbish down at the gathering .
- Easy on the onions , Harry .
- [ Harry ] No worries .
- Oy , dad .
- [ Harry ] Nico , where you been , huh ?
- [ Nico ] With Linda .
- Oh , good day , Linda .
- [ Linda ] Hi .
- Welcome home .
- Thanks .
- Nico , get a cup of coffee for Linda , eh ?
- Come , look , you haven 't even eaten your egg there .
Come on , Louis , don 't play with your food .
Here look , I 'll feed you .
- What do you think of the old time , Linda ?
Not much changed huh ?
- Hardly at all .
- Well there 's a new public toilet .
Took them 20 years to get that one up .
- Change ?
( banging )
- Don 't you look at me like that , young man .
You want me to knock you through
to the middle of next week ?
Come closer so I can hit you , Jason .
( light music )
Get here and eat up .
- On the house .
- [ Linda ] A test of nerves .
- Watch this .
- [ Man ] Hey Harry , come on , hurry up .
- Two hamburgers coming up .
Nico !
- There we go .
And about time too , kid .
- I 'm sorry about your mother , Linda .
( cashier ringing )
She was a good woman , Miss Berry .
- Thanks .
- [ Harry ] She used to come in here sometimes , you know ?
- My mother ?
- Yeah .
Used to sit over in that corner
for a long while .
Just looking out of the window as if ,
as if something was on her mind , you know .
Nico liked her .
He liked her very much .
He used to sit with her .
No talking .
Just sitting .
What you gonna do with that big house now , Linda , huh ?
( birds chirping )
( thunder rumbling )
- Lance , what are you doing ?
- Hmm , watering the flowers .
- A bit ?
Come and help me take the washing in .
- I think it 's going to rain .
( fabrics flapping )
Our loves and comforts should increase
even as our days do go .
- Here , grab this .
( rain pattering )
- [ Lance ] Hope it 's a good storm , I like the rain .
( light music )
- [ Woman ] Now mother and father have gone ,
we have the problem of maintaining Montclare .
We 're determined not to sell it .
I suggested to Rita that we might turn it
into a nursing home and she seemed to like the idea .
25th of August , 1950 .
( chiming )
( thunder rumbling )
( cat mewing )
( clanging )
- Shit .
( lightning clapping )
- Can I give you a hand ?
- Oh , Connie .
I can 't close it .
We 'll have to get it repaired .
- You should be careful .
- What 's that ?
- The wires .
- Let 's get out of here .
- Do you think it 's a good idea moving
your mother 's belongings right now ?
- It 's got to be done sometime .
- The old people are a little sensitive .
It 's best when they 're all asleep .
- Whose room is this ?
- The new arrival .
- What 's she talking about ?
- Somebody 's gotta do the
flowers . - Mrs. Ryan .
Her nephew 's bringing her up tonight .
- We 've already discussed this .
I don 't want to take any more people .
- We need the money .
- Yes I know , but one more person
isn 't going to make any difference .
It 's just all too much .
- Oh no , it 's just maintenance .
And the old for their mind ,
they still love it here .
- You 're a great optimist , Connie .
I better see Mr. Collins .
( coughing )
Cold night , Mr. Collins .
How are your eyes ?
Let 's have a look .
Head back .
Look at the ceiling .
( thunder rumbling )
( booming )
- Good god .
- You 'll get soaked !
I 'll get them .
Come on , let 's get you inside .
- They 're crazy .
- You should have gone to the front entrance .
- We got lost .
The lightning nearly got us .
- You should be in bed .
- Oh , rubbish .
And miss all the fun ?
- Damn , door 's locked .
( knocking )
- Look , you 'll have to walk .
- I was locked out of the barracks .
It was teeming with rain just like this .
- [ Linda ] Cathy !
- [ Lance ] Enemy shell started exploding
all over the bloody camp .
( knocking )
- What happened ?
- The door slammed ?
- Didn 't you slip the lock ?
I 'm sorry Mr. Ryan .
You must be tired after your long journey .
This is Linda , Mr. Cooney .
Mrs. Ryan and Mr. Ryan .
- Kelvin .
- Wasn 't your Aunt happy in the last house ?
- They weren 't happy .
- Then I got back and I put it like anyone here ,
thunder was coming and explosions
all over the bloody place .
I didn 't know what the hell to do .
And you know , it doesn 't often rain in North Africa
but my god , when it does it does come down
in buckets and lumps .
- Good heavens .
- I 'll take care of Mrs. Ryan .
- Come on Lance .
- You better stay the night , Mr. Ryan .
We 've got a spare room upstairs .
- Come on .
- Well anyhow , there I was .
I 'd locked out of the barracks .
I couldn 't get in no matter how much I yelled .
- Bags with Cynthia .
- Is this the new one ?
- Yes .
- If we get any more , we 'd have to stick them
up the chimney .
- Anyhow , what can I do ?
I couldn 't get into the barracks .
I said the only thing to do is walk
back to the latrine .
While I was on the way there , halfway there
then whoah , a whacking shell just blew the dunny sky high .
( rain pattering )
- [ Woman ] Lance has been like a father to Linda .
He drove with me into town today to buy Linda
a birthday present , a red ball .
Then in his usual absent minded way
forgot to pay Mr. Foley .
I discreetly settled the bill .
Thursday .
Someone was wandering around the house last night .
I didn 't sleep .
( thunder rumbling )
( tense music )
( light music )
( birds chirping )
( water splashing )
( singing in foreign language )
- It 's from my niece .
Shelly .
- What is it ?
- I have no idea .
- Hey , turn that thing off .
You make the telly go all fuzzy .
All the fuss about ,
never stops cleaning , that woman .
- Morning .
Mrs. Collins and Lance not here yet .
- Lance usually waits till the last one 's finished .
Thinks he gets better service that way
even though the food gets cold .
- We 'll have to do something about that fallen tree .
- I 've organised it .
We 'll manage .
- I might go into town and get you some oranges .
Would you like some sherry ?
I 'll get you some sherry .
- [ Mrs. Ryan ] The dry one ?
- [ Kelvin ] The dry one .
Look I think this place is gonna do you a lot of good .
( ominous music )
( honking )
( fly buzzing )
( whistle blowing )
( woman shouting in distance )
( whistling )
- How you been ?
- Okay .
- You look great .
- Where 's your car ?
- I lost my licence .
( light music )
Here I come !
Woo !
- Yuck .
This water stinks .
I hate dead flowers .
You know I didn 't miss her at first .
She had secrets .
Here .
- Oh , thank you .
- I suppose you think I 'm like her .
- Yup .
- Unreliable .
- Mhmm .
- Unpredictable .
- Uh-huh .
- Crazy .
- Oh yes .
- Good .
- You haven 't changed .
- What has ?
- Plenty .
What do you wanna know ?
- Nothing .
- Not even that Tom 's got a new stud phone ?
Lucy Parker , the fat girl ?
- God , no .
- None in New Guinea .
- There 's a place for her .
- Doreen Lauren .
- No . ( giggling )
( mumbling )
I don 't wanna know .
- Molly Fleming .
Stepped up his bulldozer under the tracks .
And his head popped like a watermelon !
Woohoo !
( light music )
Yeehah !
( panting )
- Barney ?
Barney .
Barney !
( bird whistling )
I can hear you .
I know you 're hiding .
( tense music )
Barney ?
Barney .
I can see you .
Come on Barney , what are you doing ?
Barney ?
( gasping )
- Hello .
- There 's someone watching us .
- I can 't see anyone .
- Standing between those two trees .
- Want me to check it out ?
( groaning )
It 's all right , it 's just like a ripper .
You got any friends up there ?
- A few .
- What kind of school is it ?
- It 's a special school for emotionally disturbed kids .
- Something bugging you ?
- No .
- [ Barney ] Bullshit .
- 1 don 't know , it 's just that I feel unwelcome .
- What do you expect after so many years ?
No letters , no phone calls .
People are curious , that 's all .
Hey , there 's a party on at Pete Barker 's tonight .
You wanna come ?
- [ Linda ] Pete Barker .
- [ Barney ] Bet you haven 't had a night out
since you been back .
- And I suppose you 'll need a lift .
- True .
True .
( laughing )
- Bye bye .
Stay well .
- Linda , it 's Mr. Collins .
He 's dead .
Died in his bath .
Lance found him .
Dr. Barton 's with Lance now .
- How is he ?
- Minor stroke .
- It 's all right .
I 'm here .
- He 's resting now , Linda .
He 's gonna sleep properly soon .
- It 's okay .
- Knowing Lance , he 'll probably be up and about
in a couple days .
You heard about Collins ?
It 's his heart .
Anyway , you can safely leave all that to Connie and me .
There 's nothing you need to do .
There .
Anyway , how are things with you ?
- Coping .
Just .
- Look .
If there 's anything I can do .
- No .
- Well you have got Connie .
She 's a fine woman .
In fact during the last couple of months
of your mother 's life she practically ran
this place single handed .
- What exactly was wrong with mother ?
- Stress , anxiety .
She was worried about money , worried about Montclare .
It all contributed .
- I might sell Montclare .
- Could be a wise decision .
Be a pity though .
It 's been in the family for a long time .
Linda , I really would like to help
so why don 't you drop around to the surgery sometime .
After all , I brought you into this world
so I have some responsibility .
- Now Carol , Mrs. Comry , it 's Barney .
Yeah that 's right .
Eh ?
How long ago did she leave ?
Good .
Okay , thanks .
You don 't mind ?
- No .
Who were you talking to ?
- Um , Pete .
How 's Lance ?
- [ Linda ] He 's all right , I think .
He 's had a shock .
- Don 't bother changing , we should get going .
- It won 't take me a sec .
Almost there .
( car honking )
Oh , who 's that ?
- I think it 's Carol .
- Carol ?
What 's she doing here ?
- Well , actually she 's running us to the party .
- Not Carol .
- I 'll tell her to get gone .
- Well , I don 't think I 'll come tonight , Barney .
- Look , it 's no trouble .
- No really , I should stay and look after Lance .
I 'm worried about him .
- Have a nice day ?
- Terrific .
- We could probably squeeze you in the back
if you had a loose end .
- No , I 'm exhausted .
I 'll probably fall asleep .
- Suit yourself .
- [ Barney ] Sure you don 't wanna change your mind ?
- [ Carol ] Come on , Barnes .
- Barnes ?
- Oh , bloody keys !
Honey , sick with your band ?
Sleep tight .
( honking )
( insects chirping )
- [ Connie ] Shouldn 't you tell Linda at least ?
- [ Dr. Barton ] What for ?
It was just a coincidence .
- [ Connie ] If you 're sure .
- [ Dr. Barton ] I was here then , you weren 't .
Trust me .
Come here .
( knocking )
- [ Connie ] Come in .
- Not going out , Linda ?
- No , I changed my mind .
I can look after things here if you two want to ,
- Ah , that 's very kind of you .
- Hettie 's gone for the weekend .
- We 'll manage .
- I 'm sure you will .
- Night then , enjoy yourselves .
- Thank you , Linda .
( airy music )
( clock ticking )
( sighing )
( chiming )
( cat meowing )
- Hey , what do you want ?
Hmm ?
Aw .
Dame .
( tense music )
Ooh .
Bye .
Dr. R. B.
Rita ?
250 .
R.B. Rita ?
Doctor R.B.
Barton ?
Damn .
( gasping )
( cat mewing )
Here , puss , puss .
Puss , puss .
Here , kitty , kitty , kitty .
Here , puss , puss , puss , puss .
Here , kitty , kitty , Kitty , kitty .
( sighing )
Here , puss , puss , puss , puss , puss , puss , puss .
( cat mewing )
Here , kitty , kitty , Kitty , come on .
Ah , who did this ?
Oh , Mrs. Peterson , what are you doing ?
- I heard a noise , I thought that ,
- [ Linda ] It 's nothing , go back to bed .
- The lights .
- I 'm going to fix them now .
Go on , go back to bed .
( Mrs. Peterson muttering )
( creaking )
( zapping )
Spooks .
( phone ringing )
Hello ?
- [ Barney ] Linda .
- Hi , Barney .
Where are you ?
- I 'm at work .
Cold , isn 't it ?
- Is it ?
- Yeah , freezing .
I walked half a mile to find this phone box .
Look , um .
I wanna see you .
- Oh , do you ?
I 'm on my own .
- [ Barney ] Where 's Connie ?
Linda ?
- What ?
- [ Barney ] Where 's Connie ?
- She 's gone out .
- [ Barney ] Eh ?
Well where 's she gone ?
- Hey , you having a good time ?
- [ Barney ] No .
- Why not ?
Drunk ?
- Sober .
That what it is .
( phone clicking )
- What 's that ?
( heavy breathing )
( cat mewing )
Barney ?
Stay there .
- Linda ?
Can you hear me ?
Linda ?
( tense music )
Linda !
( truck zooming )
Shit .
( busy tone )
- Barney ?
( clock ticking )
How did you get down here ?
Come on .
Hurry up .
( door creaking )
( clock chiming )
( water streaming )
( tense music )
Shit .
( creature cawing )
( breathing heavily )
( knocking )
( gasping )
- Hey , shh .
It 's me , okay ?
It 's only me .
- Oh , Barney .
I don 't know what 's happening .
There was somebody in the bathroom .
- Hey .
Wake up .
( moaning )
( birds chirping )
- Now when you 've all got your hats and your capes
and your scarves on , please go straight
to the bus outside , is that clear ?
Right to the bus where you 'll be helped aboard
by Simon and myself .
Don 't leave your purse behind , dear .
Somebody 'll take that .
Does everybody got a warm thing ?
- I can 't hear you .
- We 're going on a lovely scenic tour .
- We 're going on a scenic tour , darling .
Out in the bus , outside .
See , out there .
- Lance ?
( men chattering )
- Come on ladies , come on ladies .
- Someone missing , Simon ?
We seem to be a couple short .
- Couple short ?
( puppet mumbling )
( laughing )
- Not really joking , that koala , you know ,
I saw that blokes ' lips move .
( men chattering )
- Lance .
Let 's get you back to bed .
I think they all went .
Pity you missed out .
Suppose you wouldn 't have gone anyway , would you ?
Did you open your window last night ?
I went over the accounts .
They 're a real mess .
How do you feel ?
You remember my aunt Rita ?
When did she die ?
- No , no .
- What 's that ?
- Didn 't die .
( car honking )
- Oh , it 's Carol .
I 'll look in on you later .
( car revving )
Carol ?
Connie ?
- Over here .
- Did you see who was driving Carol just now ?
- Was she here ?
- Course she was here .
Her beret was in the pond this morning .
- Oh ?
- There was someone in the house last night .
Someone turned off the lights
and all the taps in my room were left running .
- Why would she do that ?
- She ?
- You said Carol was here .
- Carol .
- It 's probably one of the old folk .
You look tired .
- Why was I told my aunt Rita was dead ?
- Isn 't she ?
It was all before my time .
- There was someone in the house .
- Well if you like , I 'll report it .
Will you be back for tea ?
( bird cawing )
- [ Man ] You take care of your mother now , you hear ?
- No answer .
- Where do you think she is ?
- I don 't know .
She had a too bit to drink last night .
- There was someone driving her car .
- Hey , you gotta get out of that house .
If you like , you can stay at my place .
- No .
- Right .
Well the voluntary bush fire brigade
is holding its annual meeting at the hall tonight .
Could be a bit of a hoot .
Plus a good fire out .
- [ Dr.Barton ] She did die .
- When ?
- [ Dr.Barton ] Does it matter ?
- Yes .
- Why ?
- Because she 's my aunt .
My family .
I need to know .
- She 's dead .
Isn 't that enough ?
I know you 're very fond of Lance
but he 's a confused old man .
Ever since his first stroke he 's been living
more and more in the past .
Well , what he remembers of the past .
- But he said she didn 't die .
- Not in Montclare , no .
Your mother couldn 't cope , Linda ,
because your aunt was a very sick woman .
Finally she had to be sent to a home .
And that 's where she died .
- In some of the account books ,
there are recent payments made out to her
care of you .
- Linda .
You know what your mother was like with the accounts .
They 're a mess .
Listen .
Connie rang me , she 's very worried about you .
Are you sleeping okay ?
- [ Linda ] Fine .
- Don 't go digging into the past , Linda .
It 's gone , forget it .
( tense fast paced music )
- Who 's there ?
Is there anyone ?
- Linda ?
- There was someone in my room .
- There 's no one here .
- Wearing my mother 's coat in my room !
- The house is empty .
- I saw someone .
- Linda , what are you saying ?
There 's only Lance and myself .
- And Lance is , is asleep .
- [ Woman ] I have no strength to write now .
My mind is wandering .
I cannot live with that memory of the past anymore
yet the terrible pain of memory increases .
Connie is concerned about me .
I have spent the past week in bed .
( knocking )
- Would you like a cup of tea ?
- No .
- You should try getting some sleep .
Can I get you anything ?
- No , I 'm fine .
( bird cawing )
- [ Woman ] I am returning to the past so much now .
Yet I cannot erase from my mind
the events of those fearful days 20 years ago .
I have been hearing noises in the house .
Strange sounds all night long that keep me awake .
Lights going on and off .
Taps left running .
My door was open during the night .
I have not slept .
There is something evil in this house .
Something that lives and breathes the same air .
Linda somehow wandered into the bathroom
to discover the body of Mr. Holden
lying in the bath .
Drowned .
This morning , my friend , Frida Cartwright
was found dead in her bath .
What is happening ?
And now I know there is evil here in this house .
Mr. Carmady was found in the bathroom , dead .
It is nearly dawn .
I 'm afraid to sleep .
The house is full of whispering .
Dr. Barton came again today .
- [ Dr. Barton ] Where is she ?
- [ Connie ] Upstairs .
- [ Dr. Barton ] Where 's everybody else ?
- The bus broke down , they 've billeted out for the night .
- Good .
- Waterman .
Thompson .
Cartwright .
Leslie , Holden .
Carmady .
Cause of death , pneumonia ?
Sclerosis ?
Coma ?
Barton .
Barton , Barton .
- [ Connie ] I tried to get hold of you earlier .
She was in her room all afternoon .
She was very upset .
- She found out I was lying .
- Does it matter now ?
- Of course it matters .
- [ Connie ] Someone 's been at the files .
I gotta look at this .
( breathing heavily )
- What are you doing ?
( gasping )
- There 's , there 's marks on the neck .
Scratches .
You said it was a heart attack .
- Linda , those marks were made by Connie
and the other residents trying to lift him
out of the bath .
- Don 't come near me .
- Tell her , you must !
- Linda , take it easy .
Linda !
( tense music )
( dramatic music )
- There 's no reason why we can 't be in the top three .
Let 's not come seventh like last year .
And as you know , I 'm at the top of the game
entering into the regional competition .
Last of all fellows , it relies on teamwork .
I want you to be familiar with the equipment on both trucks .
The Old Austin and the Inter .
If there 's anything you 're still not sure about ,
just talk to Ken or myself .
But for Christ 's sake ,
- Barney !
- [ Man ] For Christ 's sake , don 't just shrug something off
as hard X Joe bloke 's job . - Barney !
- [ Man ] Because Joe Blow 's probably off
doing someone else 's job , all right ?
- Barney !
- Winning means teamwork !
Less drinking and more thinking .
If for some reason you can 't make it next Saturday
because you plan on having a fight
with your missus or something ,
George , do you wanna ?
- For Christ 's sake !
( dramatic music )
- I don 't know .
- Listen to me .
Look at me .
Look at me !
Hey , stop it .
Listen to me .
You 're fine .
Okay ?
Calm down .
All right ?
You calm ?
Okay .
Just listen to me , all right ?
We 're gonna go for a little walk .
Then we 're gonna talk about this thing , okay ?
Just you and me , all right ?
Okay ?
( tense music )
So who are we going to worry ?
Woof the dog , flagged out nurse ,
or a bunch of old buggers ?
Nothing much to worry about there , is it ?
( owl hooting )
- Barney , do you believe me ?
- Nope .
Yeah .
Hup !
So where do I find these papers ?
Desk ?
- Connie 's desk .
I put them in the drawer .
I think I 'll stay here .
- All right .
You get scared , just give us a yell .
- Barney .
What if ?
- Don 't worry .
If we have to , we 'll get the whole buddy fire brigade
to come down and piss on them .
- Barney !
Barney !
Barney ?
Barn ?
( ominous music )
( screaming )
Lance !
It 's me , hurry .
He 's coming .
Hurry .
Run .
( knocking )
Lance , hurry !
( breathing heavily )
Go !
( clock ticking )
( steps clacking )
( clicking )
( creaking )
- Who is it ?
- This is my house , Linda .
I lived here , once .
20 years , they sent me away .
- Rita .
- It was your mother .
She was the one .
She and Barton , they signed the papers ,
sent me away .
They wasted my life .
Do you know all the time , she was the one .
She was the mad one .
- No , no !
- It 's all right .
There , there .
Shh .
There .
It 's all right .
It 'll all be over soon .
( ominous music )
( shouting )
- No !
No !
No , no !
Stay off !
( banging )
( shouting )
( screaming )
( bashing )
( banging )
- [ Rita ] Junior !
( Rita laughing maniacally )
I can see you .
( laughing )
Get away !
Linda .
( ominous music )
( screaming )
( fast paced music )
( tyres screeching )
( crashing )
( revving )
( zooming )
( banging )
- Nico !
Harry , its me !
( pinball machine dinging )
Harry , Harry !
- Can 't you hear them ?
- Where 's Harry ?
- Why ?
- Where is he ?
- [ Nico ] Gone out shooting rabbits .
( dinging )
- Lock the door .
- Why ?
- Lock it .
Has Harry got another gun ?
- [ Nico ] Yes .
- Get it .
- [ Nico ] Why ?
- Just get it .
( banging )
Shut the door after you .
Hurry !
- Like a coffee ?
Hamburger ?
Bowl of grubble ?
Did you and Barney have an argument ?
Holly waffle ?
Kit kat ?
Minties ?
An ice cream ?
Chicken roll ?
Pasti ?
( gentle music )
( crashing )
Holy shit !
( shattering )
( car ignition firing )
( creaking and crashing )
( zapping )
( gun firing )
Linda !
Let 's get out of here !
Linda , Linda !
Come on , hurry !
Come on .
( intense music )
( booming )
( booming in distance )